Tom Robbins Papers, 1971-2009, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Tom Robbins Papers, 1971-2009, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 90
17 Linear Feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Tom Robbins in 1999-2000 with subsequent donations. Libby Burke, a friend of Robbins from Seattle, Washington, donated a number of articles by and about Tom Robbins from various Seattle publications.
Biographical Information
Tom Robbins (1936-) is an American author based in Seattle who has published eight novels in a style described as satirical, non-linear, and often wildly poetic. He is probably best known for Even Cowgirls Get the Blues published in 1976 and made into a 1993 film that starred Uma Thurman and a large cast of notable stars. Robbins was the narrator of the film. He has also published a children's book and a collection of non-fiction essays, reviews, and short stories
Robbins was born July 22, 1936 in Blowing Rock, North Carolina. His parents were George Thomas Robbins and Katherine Belle Robinson. He has two younger sisters. The Robbins family moved to Warsaw, Virginia in 1942. After he graduated in 1950 from Hargrace Military Academy in Chatham, Virginia, Robbins enrolled at Washington and Lee University. He left that school after his sophomore year and elnisted in the Air Force in 1953. He spent a year in Korea and two years in the Special Weather Intelligence unit of the Strategic Air Command in Nebraska. He was discharged in 1957 and returned to Virginia where he enrolled at Richmond Professional Institute (RPI is the forerunner to Virginia Commonwealth University).
Robbins lived in Richmond's Fan District and became part of the local bohemian art scene. He was a regular at a number of bars on W. Grace Street, including the Village Cafe. He was an editor for the RPI student newspaper, the Proscript. He even wrote a column for the paper, Robbin's Nest and Walks on the Wild Side, which contained early elements of his characteristic irreverent writing style.
He graduated from RPI with a degree in journalism in 1959. He worked briefly for the Richmond Times-Dispatch as a copy editor before moving to Seattle in 1962 to seek a Master's degree at the Far East Institute of the University of Washington. In Seattle for the next several years he held a number of jobs including working for the Seattle Magazine; and hosted a weekly undergground radio show at KRAB-FM. Robbins said that it was in 1967, while writing a review of a Doors concert, that he found his literary voice.
In the late 1960s he moved to South Bend, Washington, where he wrote his first novel. In 1970, Robbins moved to La Conner, Washington where he has written his subsequent work. He has been married to Alexa D'Avalon since 1987. He has three sons, all from previous marriages.
Robbins has published non-fiction essays in national magazines, including Esquire and Playboy, as well as regional Seattle periodicals. His first novel, Another Roadside Attraction, was published in 1971.
A Bibliography of Robbins' monographs:
Guy Anderson, photographs by Bob Peterson, designed by Don Scott: Gear Works Press, 1965. First book written by Robbins.
Another Roadside Attraction, Balantine, New York, 1971.
Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, Houghton Mifflin, Boston, 1976.
Still-Life with Woodpecker, Bantam, New York, 1980.
Jitterbug Perfume, Bantam, New York, 1984.
Skinny Legs and All, Bantam, New York, 1990.
Half Asleep In Frog Pajamas, Bantam, New York, 1994.
Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Bantam, New York, 2000.
Villa Incognito, Bantam, New York, 2003.
B Is for Beer, Bantam, New York, 2009.
Wild Ducks Flying Backward: The Short Writings of Tom Robbins, Bantam, New York, 2005.
Conversations with Tom Robbins, edited by Liam O. Purdon and Beef Torrey, University Press of Mississippi, 2001.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of the literary manuscripts for all of Robbins' novels and a few of his other works. It includes hand writeen drafts; typed versions of drafts; and galley proofs. There is a small collection of correspondence to Robbins from his fans, dating 1997 through 2006; some correspondence from Robbins from 2006; and journal and newspaper articles written by or about Robbins from various Seattle publications and others, dating 1967-1978.
Arrangement
The collection is organized with the seven novels in chronological order, with later donations of newspaper writings filed in chronological order and followed by fan correspondence.
Contents List
- Another Roadside Attraction, My Original Typescript, undated. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Another Roadside Attraction, Typescript, undated. (Box-folder 1:2-3)
- Another Roadside Attraction, Galley Proofs, 1970 October 31. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 1:5-6)
- Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, Typescript, undated. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, Galley Proofs with edits, undated. (Box-folder 2:3)
- Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, Galley Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 2:4)
- Still Life with Woodpecker, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Still Life with Woodpecker, Galley Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 3:1-3)
- Still Life with Woodpecker, Galley Proofs, photocopy, undated. (Box-folder 3:4-5)
- Jitterbug Perfume, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 3:6)
- Jitterbug Perfume, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 4:1)
- Jitterbug Perfume, Galley Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 4:2)
- Skinny Legs and All Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 4:3-5)
- Skinny Legs and All, Typescripts with edits and notes, unitdate. (Box-folder 5:1)
- Skinny Legs and All, Galley Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 5:2-3)
- Skinny Legs and All, Galley Proofs, second set, undated. (Box-folder 5:4-5)
- Half Asleep in Frog Pajamas, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 5:6)
- Half Asleep in Frog Pajamas, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 6:1-2)
- Half Asleep in Frog Pajamas, Galley Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 6:3-5)
- Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Handwritten notebooks, undated. (Box-folder 7:1-4)
- Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Galley Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 7:5-7)
- Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Duplicate pages from version 2, undated. (Box-folder 7:8)
- Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Galley Proofs, second set, undated. (Box-folder 7:9)
- Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Galley Proofs, second set, undated. (Box-folder 8:1-3)
- Fierce Invalids Home from Hot Climates, Style Sheets and Answers to Queries, undated. (Box-folder 8:4)
- Villa Incognito Handwritten notebooks, undated (Box-folder 8:5-6)
- Villa Incognito Galley Proofs, first set, undated. (Box-folder 8:7-8)
- Villa Incognito, Galley Proofs, 2002 September 18. (Box-folder 8:9-10)
- Text written and spoken by Robbins in Song entitled Colpevoli de Ghetto on Fouri dal Controllo by Italian rock band Gang, undated. (Box-folder 8:11)
- Foreword from The Jewelry of Ken Coryundated. (Box-folder 8:12)
- Moonlight Whoopie Cushion Sonata, undated. (Box-folder 8:13)
- The Towers of St. Ignatz-a script treatment for a feature film, undated. (Box-folder 8:14)
- Triplets (for Laurie Parker) undated. (Box-folder 8:15)
- Miscellaneous Writings, undated. (Box-folder 8:16)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backward, Page Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 9:1)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards Revised Page Proofs, undated. (Box-folder 9:2)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards materials, with miscellaneous writings, undated. (Box-folder 9:3)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards Copyedited manuscript, undated. (Box-folder 9:4)
- Villa Incognito version labeled Uncorrected and Incomplete, undated. (Box-folder 9:5)
- Typescript: six pages of Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, by Tom Robbins, undated. (Box-folder 10:1)
- The Cardinal, vol.20, no.12, Skagit Valley College, Mt. Vernon, Washington, An Intergalactic Confrontation with Tom Robbins, interview with Robbins by Peter MacKenzie, 1973 April 17 (Box-folder 10:2)
- Helix, vol.1, no 2., Seattle, Washington 1967 April. (Box-folder 10:3)
- Helix, [date determined by date of Country Joe and the Fish concert advertisement] includes advertisement of radio show hosted by Tom Robbins, page 7, Seattle, Washington, [cover of magazine has Native American] 1967 June 11 (Box-folder 10:3)
- Helix, Seattle, Washington 1968. (Box-folder 10:4)
- Helix, [Sky River Rock Festival and Lighter than Air Fair cover issue] Seattle, Washington, 1968. (Box-folder 10:5)
- Helix, vol. 3, no. 7, Seattle, Washington, 1968 May 9. (Box-folder 10:6)
- Helix, vol. 3, no. 10, Seattle Washington, 1968 June 20. (Box-folder 10:7)
- Helix, vol 4., no. 1, Seattle, Washington, 1968 July 3. (Box-folder 10:8)
- One page newspaper poster on dancing, possible from Helix, undated. (Box-folder 10:9)
- One page newspaper poster entitled Hippie Emigration, possibly from Helix, undated. (Box-folder 10:10)
- The Nation, [two pages] review of Even Cowgirls Get the Blues, by Ann Comeron, 1976 August 28. (Box-folder 10:11)
- Northwest Passage, vol. 10, no. 8, Bellingham, Washington, The Toadstool That Conquered the Universe, by Tom Robbins, 1974 March 25-April 8. (Box-folder 10:12)
- Richmond Times-Dispatch, [one page] Tom Robbins' Second Already Sold Out, by Maurice Duke, 1976 June 27. (Box-folder 10:13)
- Rolling Stone, no. 252, includes the article Tom Robbins Gets the Last Laugh, by Michael Rogers, 1977 November 17. (Box-folder 10:14)
- Seattle-Post Intelligencer, newspaper clipping,Rock Group Touches off Flower Festival, by Tom Robbins [includes drawing of Country Jow and the Fish], 1967 June 9 (Box-folder 10:15)
- Seattle-Post Intelligencer, newspaper clipping, on the piano dump benefit concert for Helix, 1968 April 19. (Box-folder 10:16)
- Seattle-Post Intelligencer, Book World and the Arts section, review of Robbins'Another Roadside Attraction, by Frank Chesley and article Travelling with Tom Robbins, by Donovan Cook, 1971 May 16. (Box-folder 10:17)
- Seattle-Post Intelligencer, Book World Arts section, Gertrude Pacific-Goddess of the On-ramp, by Tom Robbins, 1972 April 16. (Box-folder 10:18)
- Washington Star, calendar section, Tom Robbins, the Story Teller Who Lives in a Tree, by Randy Sue Coburn, 1976 June 29. (Box-folder 10:19)
- The Weekly, Seattle, vol. 1, no. 3, Tom Robbins Rides Again by Robert Downey, 1976 April 14 (Box-folder 10:20)
- The Weekly, Seattle, Notes on Nukes, Nookie, and Neo-Romanticism by Tom Robbins, 1978 June 21. (Box-folder 10:21)
- The Weekly, Seattle, review of Oklahoma! by Roger Downey, 1981, September 9-15. (Box-folder 10:22)
- The Weekly, Seattle, Papa [Karl] Wallends, Only the flying shadow of his 'perfection of a conscious act of craziness' made it to the Kingdome, by Tom Robbins, 1978 April 5-11. (Box-folder 10:23)
- Newspaper clipping of column by Rick Anderson mentioning Tom Robbins, undated. (Box-folder 10:24)
- Newspaper clipping, Another Roadside Attraction article on Robbins visit to Western State College's Whole Earth Festival Celebration, undated. (Box-folder 10:25)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box-folder 11:1)
- Correspondence, 1997. (Box-folder 11:2)
- Correspondence, 1998. (Box-folder 11:3)
- Correspondence, 1999. (Box-folder 11:4)
- Correspondence, 2000. (Box-folder 11:5)
- Correspondence, 2001. (Box-folder 11:6)
- Correspondence, 2002. (Box-folder 11:7)
- Correspondence, 2003. (Box-folder 11:8)
- Correspondence, 2004. (Box-folder 11:9)
- Correspondence, 2005. (Box-folder 11:10)
- Correspondence, 2006. (Box-folder 11:11)
- Correspondence, from Robbins 2006. (Box-folder 11:12)
- Correspondence, miscellaneous, scraps of paper, etc., undated. (Box-folder 11:13)
- Article by Robbins about B is for Beer (manuscript and newspaper copy) for the Seattle-Post Intelligencer, 2007 May. (Box-folder 12:1)
- Best Seller lists regarding B is for Beer, undated. (Box-folder 12:2)
- Contracts and Correspondence, 1993-2007. (Box-folder 12:3)
- Corrections to B is for Beer, undated. (Box-folder 12:4)
- Illustrations for B is for Beer, undated. (Box-folder 12:5)
- Interview transcript- Robbins with Harper Collins on B is for Beer, undated. (Box-folder 12:6)
- Miscellaneous materials, undated. (Box-folder 12:7)
- Introduction by Robbins for the 2006 edition of Siddhartha by Hermen Hesse, undated, circa 2006. (Box-folder 12:8)
- The New Yorker, cartoon, I doubt a children's book about beer would sell,2007 January 22 (Box-folder 12:9)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, complete with edits, undated. (Box-folder 12:10-12)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, complete, two copies including illustrations, undated. (Box-folder 12:13)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, chapters 3-18, including one illustration, undated. (Box-folder 12:14)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, chapters 5-18, undated. (Box-folder 12:15)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, page 68 and suggested catalog copy, undated. (Box-folder 12:16)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, pages unidentified, undated. (Box-folder 12:17)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, proofed-complete, undated. (Box-folder 12:18)
- B is for Beer, Galley Proofs, proofed-two copies, one copy includes chapters 1-9, second copy includes chapters 1-5, undated. (Box-folder 12:19)
- B is for Beer (chapters 2, 3, 4, and part of 5)-Handwritten Manuscript, undated. (Box-folder 12:20)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards, corrections, undated. (Box-folder 12:21)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards, Galley Proofs: written on title page: Mis to late Feb.-design paper; March 10-proofs; April 20-second pair of proofs,undated, circa 2009. (Box-folder 12:22)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards, Galley Proof with edits, undated. (Box-folder 12:23)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards, cover page, contents, dedication, quote, undated. (Box-folder 12:24)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards, Travel Articles, chapters 1-5, undated. (Box-folder 12:25)
- Wild Ducks Flying Backwards,Tributes, chapters 6-25, undated. (Box-folder 12:26)